<!-- Bloomington, IL 2014 -->
<!-- Open Data Policies for Sunlight Foundation -->
<!-- StateDecoded XML Examples: http://docs.statedecoded.com/xml-format.html-->

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>
    <structure>
        <unit label="section" identifier="bloomingtonil" level="1">Bloomington, IL </unit>
    </structure>
    <section_number>Bloomington, IL (2014)</section_number> <!--citystateyear, no spaces-->
    <catch_line>Legislation (2014)</catch_line>
    <text>
<!--insert text of the policy below this line  -->

<p>FOR COUNCIL: August 25, 2014</p> <p>SUBJECT: Website Transparency Policy</p> <p>RECOMMENDATION/MOTION: That the Ordinance be passed.</p> <p>STRATEGIC PLAN LINK: Goal 1. Financially sound City providing quality basic services.</p> <p>STRATEGIC PLAN SIGNIFICANCE: Objective 1c. Engaged residents that are well informed and involved in an open governance process.</p> <p>BACKGROUND: The Illinois Policy Institute has developed a Ten-Point Transparency Checklist to help provide a “best practices” framework to improve government transparency across the State of Illinois. This Checklist encourages the following information to be provided on a public body’s website: (1) Elected & Administrative Officials: Contact Information; (2) Meeting Information: Calendar (Future) Minutes & Board Packets (Past); (3) Public Records: FOIA submission & FOIA Officer Contact Information; (4) Budgets: General and Special Projects; (5) Financial Audits: Comprehensive Annual Financial Reports; (6) Expenditures: Bills & Payroll; (7) Salary & Benefits: Wages, Salary, Overtime, Health, Dental, Life, Pension, etc.; (8) Contracts: Union, Private Contractors, Vendors, Council Contract; (9) Lobbying: TaxpayerFunded Lobbying Associations; and (10) Taxes & Fees: Sales, Property, Income, and Miscellaneous Taxes, Non-proprietary in excess of $25,000.</p> <p>The City is committed to transparency in the conduct of the public’s business. It should be noted that in 2013, Bloomington was one (1) of only fifty (50) of the nearly 7,000 communities in Illinois to earn the Illinois Policy Institute’s Sunshine Award for outstanding online transparency performance. Upon final audit, Bloomington earned 88.7 points out of 100, an improvement of thirty (30) points over the City’s first audit score, and finished in ninth place overall for web transparency in the State of Illinois.</p> <p>City staff has modeled a Website Transparency Policy based off the Illinois Policy Institute’s checklist. This Policy was previously reviewed by the Council at a Committee of the Whole meeting at which time there was a desire communicated to have it adopted by Ordinance as opposed by Resolution and to make sure that City staff had sufficient time to implement the changes set forth within the Policy. The Resolution has now been modified into an Ordinance and the Policy itself has been updated to provide further clarification on some of the issues and ensure staff has sufficient time to implement the changes. </p> <p>As opposed to a September 1, 2014 start date, the Policy now calls for implementation effective October 1, 2014. The new version of the Policy also has a standard five (5) year retention policy for all documents. Clarification within the Policy was also made on the requirement that executed contracts, entered into by the Council on or after October 1, 2014, will be placed on the City’s website. It is staff’s intent that once these contracts are executed by all parties, they will be scanned and placed in the appropriate folder on the website. Older contracts will be scanned and placed on the website as resources allow. The revised Policy also clarifies that information on construction and building permits and application fees, along with written applications, will be available on the website. Other permits, fees and applications will be added and provided as available. </p> <p>The transparency portal on the City’s website will be updated as a result of this Policy to coordinate with the ten (10) areas it outlines. Links will be provided under each category to obtain the information described within the Policy. A large majority of the information detailed within the Policy is already on the website and in many cases the City will be exceeding the Policy’s written standards. Staff is hopeful that by adding even more information to the website and clarifying where documents can be found, there will be a reduction in FOIA requests.</p> <p>COMMUNITY GROUPS/INTERESTED PERSONS CONTACTED: This Policy was drafted based on recommendations from the Illinois Public Policy Institute.</p> <p>FINANCIAL IMPACT: Not applicable.</p> <p>AN ORDINANCE ADOPTING A CITY WEBSITE TRANSPARENCY POLICY</p> <p>BE IT ORDAINED BY THE CITY COUNCIL OF THE CITY OF BLOOMINGTON, ILLINOIS:</p> <p>WHEREAS, the City Council recognizes the importance and the need for an open and transparent government to serve its residents; and</p> <p>WHEREAS, the Illinois Policy Institute is a “non-partisan research organization dedicated to supporting public policy initiatives for a better Illinois.”</p> <p>WHEREAS, the Illinois Policy Institute describes itself, “as a leading voice for economic liberty and government accountability, the Institute engages policy makers, opinion leaders and citizens on the state and local level.”</p> <p>WHEREAS, the Illinois Policy Institute has developed its Ten-Point Transparency Checklist to hold government and elected officials accountable to the taxpaying public. In addition, this checklist will provide a “best practices” framework to improve government transparency across the State of Illinois.</p> <p>WHEREAS, the Illinois Policy Institute’s Ten Point Checklist is a proactive guideline to ensure that government bodies freely share the identified information with the public.</p> <p>WHEREAS, the Ten-Point Transparency Checklist includes but is not limited to the following: (1) Elected & Administrative Officials: Contact Information; (2) Meeting Information: Calendar (Future) Minutes & Board Packets (Past); (3) Public Records: FOIA submission & FOIA Officer Contact Information; (4) Budgets: General and Special Projects; (5) Financial Audits: Comprehensive Annual Financial Reports; (6) Expenditures: Bills & Payroll; (7) Salary & Benefits: Wages, Salary, Overtime, Health, Dental, Life, Pension, etc.; (8) Contracts: Union, Private Contractors, Vendors, Council Contract; (9) Lobbying: TaxpayerFunded Lobbying Associations; and (10) Taxes & Fees: Sales, Property, Income, and Miscellaneous Taxes, Non-proprietary in excess of $25,000.</p> <p>WHEREAS, the City Council is committed to transparency in the conduct of the public’s business; and</p> <p>WHEREAS, utilizing the Illinois Policy Institutes the City Council has developed standards for the City website to provide the public with information in an accountable and transparent manner; and</p> <p>NOW THEREFORE, BE IT ORDAINED BY THE CITY COUNCIL OF THE CITY OF BLOOMINGTON, ILLINOIS:</p> <p>SECTION 1. That the above recitals are hereby incorporated into the body of this Ordinance and restated as though set forth herein.</p> <p>SECTION 2. The City’s Website Transparency Policy, attached hereto and made a part of as Exhibit “A”, is hereby adopted by the City Council.</p> <p>SECTION 3. In the event that any section, clause, provision, or part of this Ordinance shall be found and determined to be invalid by a court of competent jurisdiction, all valid parts that are severable from the invalid parts shall remain in full force and effect.</p> <p>SECTION 4. The City Clerk is hereby authorized to publish this ordinance in pamphlet form as provided by law.</p> <p>SECTION 5. This ordinance shall be effective immediately after the date of its publication as required by law.</p> <p>SECTION 6. This ordinance is passed and approved pursuant to the home rule authority granted Article VII, Section 6 of the 1970 Illinois Constitution.</p> <p>PASSED this 25th day of August, 2014.</p> <p>APPROVED: Tari Renner, Mayor</p> <p>EXHIBIT A</p> <p>CITY OF BLOOMINGTON WEBSITE TRANSPARENCY POLICY</p> <p>I. Purpose</p> <p>This policy provides guidance as to how the City presents public information in a transparent and accountable manner, with emphasis on openness, ethics, and fiscal responsibility. This policy is a minimum standard and should not inhibit the dissemination of other public information where appropriate. In many cases, the information contained herein, and more, is already on the City’s website and this policy is simply designed to provide a framework and baseline for the documents and information made available electronically. It is further recognized that the City’s resources are limited and in some cases compliance may be phased in as set forth within the policy. Finally, the retention dates set forth in this policy refer to recommendations from the Illinois Policy Institute and will be followed to the extent that website space allows.</p> <p>II. Effective Date</p> <p>The provisions of this Policy shall be applicable on or after October 1, 2014.</p> <p>III. Procedures/Guidelines</p> <p>As part of the commitment of the City to open, transparent and honest government, the City website at www.cityblm.org shall include the following information and documents accessed by a link named “Transparency” on the website homepage.</p> <p>1. Elected & Administrative Officials.</p> <p>The City website shall include contact information, including name, department or office, job title, mailing address, facsimile number, telephone number, and an electronic contact method for all elected City Council members. The contact information for the City Manager and each City Department shall also be listed on the website. The website shall finally contain a listing of all other City boards and commissions and the names of the individuals appointed to serve on same.</p> <p>2. Meeting information</p> <p>The City website shall comply with the Illinois Open Meetings Act. The City website shall include the annual meeting schedule and monthly calendar for all meetings of the City Council and the City controlled boards and commissions. The website shall also include agendas, packets, minutes, audio and video recordings of all open sessions of City Council meetings. Meeting dates may be changed and meetings may be canceled, subject to the requirements of the Open Meetings Act. The City shall use its best efforts to promptly update the City’s website to notify the public of any canceled or rescheduled meetings.</p> <p>The City Council meeting agendas, packets and minutes shall remain available on the City’s website for a minimum of five (5) years after completion of the City Council meeting. Audio and video recordings of open sessions of City Council meetings shall remain on the City’s website for at least one calendar year after completion of the City Council meeting. Once per year, the City Clerk may remove audio and video recordings that have been on the City’s website for at least one calendar year as authorized by law. Subsequently, the City Clerk may apply to the Illinois Records Commission for disposal of all audio and video recordings of open sessions that have been removed from the City’s website.</p> <p>Previous City Council meeting packets and minutes shall remain on the City’s website for a minimum of five years.</p> <p>3. Public Records / FOIA Requests</p> <p>The City website shall include the name, department or office, job title, mailing address, telephone number, and an electronic contact method for all City Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) Officers, along with the mailing address, facsimile number, and electronic submission method for FOIA requests.</p> <p>4. Budgets</p> <p>The City website shall include the detailed budget for the current fiscal year, along with the detailed budgets for a minimum of five prior fiscal years. This information is to be listed on the City’s website in a user-friendly format (e.g., listed and/or searchable) as possible and/or resources allow.</p> <p>5. Financial Audits</p> <p>The City website shall include the City’s Annual Audited Financial Reports for a minimum of five years after the City’s auditor presents the Audited Financial Report to the City Council. This information is to be listed on the City’s website in a user-friendly format (e.g., listed and/or searchable) as possible and/or resources allow.</p> <p>6. Expenditures</p> <p>The City website shall include the City’s bi-monthly claims reports, which shall include, where applicable, bills processed for all City funds presented within the City’s annual financial statements, including bills and payroll applicable to special revenue, debt service, capital project, enterprise, agency and internal service funds (as well as special funds). This shall be in the form of the Bills & Payroll Report. The Report shall be in a searchable format and shall include the name of the payee, the amount of expenditure, and the line item and/or account number. The Bills & Payroll Report will remain on the City’s website for a minimum of five years after the City Council has approved the Report. </p> <p>7. Salary & Benefits</p> <p>Starting with Fiscal Year 2013, the City website shall display total compensation for each City budgeted position per fiscal year in a searchable format. Each City budgeted position will be displayed by position and department or office. City paid benefits shall be shown in separate categories, including, total compensation, budgeted salary, clothing allowance, health and dental insurance, life insurance, pension, FICA, and Medicare. In addition, annual vacation days, annual personal and sick days, and annual number of holidays will be shown for each City budgeted position. This information shall be updated as required by law and shall remain available on the City’s website for a minimum of five years after the information has been posted on the City’s website.</p> <p>8. Contracts</p> <p>The City website shall include a copy of all executed vendor contracts in excess of $25,000 entered into by the City Council on or after October 1, 2014, which shall remain available on the City’s website for five years after the contracts have been executed by the parties. Existing agreements or contracts with the City (i.e., those in existence prior to October 1, 2014 and in excess of $25,000) shall be placed onto the City’s website as City staff is able to do so and as resources allow. City staff shall also attempt to categorize the contracts and agreements and make access to said contracts and agreements searchable if resources allow. Those contracts involving proprietary matters and/or information shall not be placed on the City’s website.</p> <p>The City website shall also display the current union contracts for all bargaining units. The union contracts will remain posted on the website until a new union contract is approved and ratified by the bargaining unit and the City Council.</p> <p>The City website shall also include a section on the City’s procurement services, including how to do business with the City and any current request for proposals or bidding opportunities offered by the City.</p> <p>9. Lobbying</p> <p>The City Council does not currently have a contract with a certified lobbyist. If the City ever enters into a lobbying contract, it will be posted on the City’s website in accordance with Section 8. In addition, the City Council, Elected Officials and multiple departments may have memberships with various associations. Any contracts with those associations will be posted in accordance with Section 8 and payments made to those associations posted in accordance with Section 6.</p> <p>10. Taxes and Fees</p> <p>The City website shall contain a section on local tax information. This section shall include information on the City’s taxes, including amusement, food and beverage, hotel/motel, motor fuel, packaged liquor, utilities, property and sales tax. This section shall be updated to coincide with any changes to existing local taxes and/or rate changes. Information on the City’s construction and building permit and application fees shall also be listed, along with any applicable written application. This information is to be listed on the City’s website in a user-friendly format (e.g., listed and/or searchable) as possible and/or resources allow.</p> <p>Cincinnati, OH</p> <p>Administrative Regulation No. 61</p> <p>Date: May 29, 2014</p> <p>Subject: OPEN DATA REQUIREMENTS AND IMPLEMENTATION PLAN</p> <p>OBJECTIVE</p> <p>The City of Cincinnati recognizes that citizens’ access to their local government’s information is fundamental to transparency and accountability. Therefore, the City of Cincinnati will make datasets about the operations and finances of government publicly available for review, interpretation, analysis, research and criticism.</p> <p>DIRECTIVE</p> <p>City departments will work in cooperation with the Department of Enterprise Technology Solutions as outlined in this Administration Regulation and its corresponding Open Data Implementation Plan (“implementation plan”) to make their respective datasets publicly available via OpenDataCincy.org. The datasets will adhere to the following principles:</p> <p>1. Complete: All facets of the data are available (unless subject to valid privacy, security or privilege limitations).</p> <p>2. Accessible: Data is easily and freely accessed via a central web portal, OpenDataCincy.org.</p> <p>3. Primary: Data is collected at the source, with the highest level of granularity (not in aggregate or modified forms).</p> <p>4. Timely: Data is available to the public in a timely manner, ideally as soon as it is collected (“real-time” data).</p> <p>5. Machine-Processable: Data is reasonably structured, based on industry data standards, to allow for automated processing.</p> <p>6. License-Free: Data must not be subject to copyright, patent or trademark or trade secret regulation.</p> <p>7. Non-Proprietary: Data must be available in a format over which no entity has exclusive control.</p> <p>OVERSIGHT & IMPLEMENTATION STRUCTURE</p> <p>Executive Committee</p> <p>The Open Data Executive Committee (“Executive Committee”) will consist of:</p> <p>1. a Chief Data Officer;</p> <p>2. an information technology manager from the Department of Enterprise Technology Solutions;</p> <p>3. an attorney from the Solicitor’s Office;</p> <p>4. a non-technical representative from the City Manager’s Office; and</p> <p>5. an analytics expert from the Department of Enterprise Technology Solutions.</p> <p>The Executive Committee will meet quarterly, or more often as is determined necessary by the Chief Data Officer.</p> <p>At least once annually, the Executive Committee shall have an open meeting at which members of the public may attend and directly provide the Executive Committee with input.</p> <p>The Executive Committee will be responsible for vetting data specific to security or privacy concerns; reviewing funding requests from the Chief Data Officer and making recommendations for funding to the Director of Enterprise Technology Solutions; and for holding the Chief Data Officer accountable to the implementation plan.</p> <p>The Executive Committee will also be responsible for conducting an annual review (or more ofien, as the Chief Data Officer recommends as necessary) of this Administration Regulation and making recommendations for revision to the City Manager, with the goal of expanding the City’s open data initiative and increasing the number of open datasets.</p> <p>Chief Data Officer</p> <p>The Chief Data Officer will be identified from existing staff of the Department of Enterprise Technology Solutions.</p> <p>The Chief Data Officer will be responsible for realizing the implementation plan as laid out in this Administrative Regulation by providing technical assistance and guidance to the Open Data Working Group, and by identifying infrastructure and resources needed to realize the implementation plan.</p> <p>The Chief Data Officer will establish standards and schedules for the publication of datasets. The overarching goal is to deliver public datasets in an efficient and cost-effective manner.</p> <p>The Chief Data Officer will review existing City policies to identify impediments to the City’s open data initiative. The Chief Data Officer will work with relevant staff, including but not limited to the City’s Information Security Officer and the Solicitor’s Office, to guide and/or propose revisions to existing policies in order to facilitate the City’s open data initiative, where greater openness can be promoted without damage to the City’s legal and financial interests.</p> <p>The Chief Data Officer will facilitate information sharing amongst City departments. Additionally, the Chief Data Officer will hold quarterly sessions, which will be open to the general public, in order to facilitate better cooperation between the City and Cincinnati’s private technology development community. The purpose of these sessions will be to solicit feedback on desired datasets not yet published in open format, and to gain a greater understanding of private-sector needs and recommendations.</p> <p>The Chief Data Officer will be responsible for making recommendations to the Executive Committee for revision to this Administrative Regulation and its implementation plan with the goal of expanding the City’s open data initiative and increasing the number of open datasets. These recommendations will be submitted, at a minimum, on an annual basis.</p> <p>The Chief Data Officer will also act as a liaison between the Open Data Working Group and the Executive Committee; provide department-by-department summary updates on a monthly basis to the Executive Committee and City Manager; provide a comprehensive annual review of the City’s open data initiative for the Executive Committee and City Manager; prepare any ad hoc reports as requested by the Mayor or City Council; make funding recommendations to the Executive Committee; and set the agenda for the executive committee’s meetings.</p> <p>The Chief Data Officer may require the Executive Committee to meet more frequently than each quarter, as the Chief Data Officer determines is necessary.</p> <p>Open Data Working Group</p> <p>The Open Data Working Group (“Working Group”) will consist of, at a minimum, one Open Data Coordinator from each of the City’s departments. Additional members may be added at the discretion of the Chief Data Officer.</p> <p>The Working Group will meet quarterly, no less than one week prior to the quarterly meetings of the Executive Committee.</p> <p>The Working Group will serve as a forum in support of the implementation plan. The Working Group will work to support the City’s open government goals, including collaborations with researchers, the private sector and the public. The Working Group will also identify problems or issues that arise during the course of their work on the implementation plan and develop recommendations for resolution to the Chief Data Officer.</p> <p>Open Data Coordinators</p> <p>Each Department will have at least one Open Data Coordinator. The Open Data Coordinator may have other job duties in addition to serving in this capacity.</p> <p>Department Directors or Division Heads may make recommendations to the Chief Data Officer on their respective departmental Open Data Coordinators; however, the Chief Data Officer will have sole discretion to select the most capable and appropriate departmental representatives to serve in that capacity.</p> <p>The Open Data Coordinators, in cooperation with their Department Director, will identify and recommend datasets for public distribution to the Chief Data Officer.</p> <p>With assistance and direction from the Chief Data Officer, the Open Data Coordinators will work to realize the implementation plan.</p> <p>Each Department’s Open Data Coordinator also will be responsible for attending quarterly meetings of the Open Data Working Group; identifying to the Chief Data Officer any potential privacy or security concerns in a dataset; and informing their Department Director of their work related to the implementation plan.</p> <p>PUBLIC RECORDS & LEGALLY PROTECTED INFORMATION</p> <p>Nothing in this Administrative Regulation shall be construed to supersede existing requirements for review and clearance of information exempt from disclosure under the Ohio Public Records Act and other applicable laws, regulations, or judicial orders.</p> <p>OPEN DATA IMPLEMENTATION PLAN</p> <p>This Open Data Implementation Plan takes effect upon the City Manager’s signing of the corresponding Administrative Regulation.</p> <p>Within 30 days</p> <p>• ETS Director identifies Chief Data Officer and members of Executive Committee</p> <p>Within 60 days</p> <p>• Chief Data Officer selects departmental Open Data Coordinators</p> <p>. Chief Data Officer provides first summary update to Executive Committee</p> <p>Within 90 days</p> <p>• Joint meeting of ETS Director, Executive Committee and Open Data Working Group</p> <p>. Departments work with Chief Data Officer to identify one dataset to publish in accordance with the open data principles outlined in the Directive of the Administrative Regulation</p> <p>• Chief Data Officer hosts open session to engage private citizens and solicit feedback</p> <p>• Chief Data Officer provides second summary update to Executive Committee</p> <p>Within 120 days</p> <p>- Chief Data Officer provides third summary update to Executive Committee</p> <p>Within 150 days</p> <p>• Chief Data Officer has identified necessary resources and infrastructure to publish one dataset per department in accordance with the open data principles outlined in the Directive of the Administrative Regulation</p> <p>• Chief Data Officer provides fourth summary update to Executive Committee</p> <p>Within 180 days</p> <p>• Chief Data Officer hosts open session to engage private citizens and solicit feedback</p> <p>• Chief Data Officer provides fifth summary update to Executive Committee</p> <p>• Meeting of the Open Data Working Group</p> <p>• Meeting of Executive Committee Within 210 days</p> <p>• Chief Data Officer has secured necessary resources and infrastructure to publish one dataset per department in accordance with the open data principles outlined in the Directive of the Administrative Regulation</p> <p>• Chief Data Officer provides sixth summary update to Executive Committee</p> <p>Within 240 days</p> <p>• Chief Data Officer provides seventh summary update to Executive Committee</p> <p>Within 270 days</p> <p>• One dataset as identified above is published in accordance with the principles outlined in the Directive of the Administrative Regulation</p> <p>• Meeting of the Open Data Working Group</p> <p>• Meeting of Executive Committee</p> <p>• Chief Data Officer hosts open session to engage private citizens and solicit feedback</p> <p>Within 300 days</p> <p>• Chief Data Officer prepares Phase 1 Progress Report on activities of Open Data Working Group and makes recommendations for updates or revisions to the Administrative Regulation, ongoing funding and support needs, implementation plan</p> <p>Within 4 years</p> <p>• All City datasets publicly available online in open format</p> <p></p>

</text>

<history>
<!-- put Notes/resolution/executive order/refernces history in this area. (Adopted on, council votes, date passed etc) --> 

Enacted: Enacted: 2014; Link: http://www.cityblm.org/Modules/ShowDocument.aspx?documentid=7183; Means: Legislation


</history>
    <!--<metadata></metadata>-->
    <tags>
        <!-- Tag if this juristiction is a city state, etc --> 
        <tag>city</tag>
        <!-- <tag>state</tag> --> 
        <!-- <tag>county</tag> -->
        <!-- <tag>executive order</tag> --> 
        
    </tags>
    </text>
</law>
